Guide to the Jacob Pat Papers WAG.127
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jacob Pat Papers
circa 1930-1978
1944-1960
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Pat, Jacob, 1890-1966
Patt, Rebecca
WAG.127
2.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 1 manuscript box and 1 oversize folder.
Jacob Pat was a journalist, writer and activist born in Bialystok, Russian Empire, in 1890. He served as the General Secretary of the Jewish Labor Bund's Central Association of Yiddish Schools in Warsaw, Poland in the years preceding World War II. A fund-raising trip in the fall of 1938 brought Jacob Pat to the United States where he was compelled to remain due to the war. He then devoted his efforts to anti-Nazi activity and rescue work and became the Executive Secretary of the Jewish Labor Comittee, a position he held until his retirement in 1963. He also served as a member of the Delegation of the Jewish Labor Bund to the U.S., and as a chairman of the Congress of Jewish Culture. These papers include correspondence, essays, writings, and photographs, in particular material pertaining to Pat's work with the Jewish Labor Committee.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Rebecca Patt, the granddaughter of Jacob Pat, in 1996. The accession number associated with this gift is 1998.005 and 1998.008.
A negative and some accompanying correspondence found in the repository was added to the collection in 2014. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.112.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Jacob Pat was born in Bialystok, Russian Empire, in 1890. He attended yeshivas in Slobodka and Slutek and later graduated from a teachers' seminary in Vilna. Active in the Zionist-Socialist Workers Party from 1905, he dropped his Zionist sympathies and became a member of the social-democratic Jewish Labor Bund after World War I. While working as a teacher, he also served as secretary of the Jewish Community Board of Bialystok, 1917-1920. He lived in Warsaw from 1921 to 1938, and worked there as General Secretary of the Bund's Central Association of Yiddish Schools (CISHO), which enrolled an estimated 60,000 children throughout Poland during the interwar years. He was a prolific journalist, editing and writing for Bundist children's magazines, and serving as co-editor for the Polish Bund's newspaper, the Folkstseitung.
In the 1930s he traveled to the United States on fund-raising trips, representing the Bund schools. One such trip took him to New York City in the fall of 1938. Worsening conditions in Europe forced him to remain in the United States to devote himself to anti-Nazi activity and rescue work. He had left behind in Warsaw his wife, Rivke Pat, and two children, Emanuel and Naomi. The family fled to Vilna after the German invasion of Poland, and there Rivke Pat died. Emanuel and Naomi Patt (this spelling of the surname was adopted by them in the U.S.) were brought to the U.S. on special visas in 1940. Jacob Pat remarried, to Frieda Wider, in 1942.
In 1941 Pat became Executive Secretary of the Jewish Labor Committee, a position he held until his retirement in 1963. He also served as a member of the Delegation of the Jewish Labor Bund to the U.S., 1938-1947, as chairman of the Congress for Jewish Culture, and as co-editor of Zukunft. In 1946 he toured displaced persons camps and visited with communities of Jewish survivors in France and Eastern Europe; he wrote about his experiences in Poland in Ashes and Fire(1947). In later years he traveled extensively to Europe, South America and Israel. He was a frequent contributor to the Jewish press both in Yiddish and English, and published a number of books, including Conversations with Jewish Writers (1959). He died in New York City on April 26, 1966.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of correspondence, including both incoming and outgoing letters which reflect Pat's involvement with a wide range of Jewish political and cultural organizations, and personal correspondence with friends from many countries. Of special note is a file of correspondence related to the publication of his Conversations with Jewish Writers, 1959-1960. Also included in the correspondence files are a small number of letters addressed to or written by other Jewish Labor Committee and Jewish Labor Bund officers and staff, which came into Pat's possession in the course of his work. The collection also includes a substantial amount of material illustrating Pat's work with the Jewish Labor Committee, manuscript and printed reports and essays on a variety of topics related to the Holocaust and Jewish survival, and records of his travels. A small number of documents dating from the years after Jacob Pat's death in 1966 were preserved by his widow, Frieda. Approximately three hundred and fifty black and white photographs document Pat's travels throughout Europe, Israel and South America on behalf of the Jewish Labor Committee and the Joint Distribution Committee. Also represented in the photographs are meetings, events and family members and friends. Notable individuals included in the photographs include Baruch Charney Vladeck, Szmul Zygielbojm and Golda Meir.
Arrangement
Organized into 3 series:
Series I: Biographical and Correspondence, 1937-1971
Series II: Subject files, 1935-1978
Series III: Photographs, circa 1930-1969.
Series I is arranged chronologically and series II and III are arranged alphabetically by subject, and thereunder chronologically.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Series I and II of the Jacob Pat Papers were microfilmed in 2005 by the OCLC Digital Collection and Preservation Services, with funding provided by the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum. Researchers must use microfilm for Series I and II of this collection; microfilm call number is Film R-7200, Reels 1-5.
Related Archival Materials
Jewish Labor Committee, Chicago Records and Photographs (WAG 160)
Jewish Labor Committee Oral History Collection (OH 027)
Jewish Labor Committee Photographs (PHOTOS 048)
Jewish Labor Committee Records, Part I: Holocaust Era Files (WAG 025.1)
Jewish Labor Committee Records, Part II: Holocaust Era Files (WAG 025.2)
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Records, Part III: Post-war Administrative Files and Anti-Discrimination Department Files (WAG 025.003)
Jewish Labor Committee Records, Part IV: Addendum (WAG 025.4)
Poland |x History |y 1918-1945.; Antisemitism |z Soviet Union |x History |y 20th century.; Labor movement |z Poland.; Political parties |z Poland.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Holocaust survivors.; Jews |x Persecutions |z Europe.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945) |z Poland.; Jewish refugees |z Hungary.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Jews -- Rescue.; Correspondence.; Demonstrations |z France |x History |y 20th century.; Australia |x History |y 1951-1965.; Jews |x Politics and government.; Soviet Union |x Foreign public opinion, French.; Jewish refugees.; Photographs.; Anti-fascist movements -- United States.; Chanin, N., d. 1965; Ogólny Żydowski Związek Robotniczy "Bund" w Polsce; Common Council for American Unity; American Labor Committee; American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee; Patt, Emanuel, 1912-1971; Pat, Jacob, 1890-1966; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.); Sherer, Emanuel; Pat, Frieda Wider.; General Jewish Council (U.S.); Held, Adolph, 1885-1969; International Jewish Labor Bund; Congress for Jewish Culture; Patt, Rebecca
- Series I: Biographical/Correspondence, 1937-1971
  - Biographical/Obituary Information, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Reel 1
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1955-Jul 1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, Aug 1955-Dec 1955 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1955-Apr 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, May 1955-Dec 1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Reel 2
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1962-May 1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1962-Dec 1962 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1966, 1972, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: Bialystoker Book, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: Related to Sihot im Soforim Yehudiyim (Conversations with Jewish Writers), 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: Sherer, Emanuel, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1935-1978
  - Address Books & Business Cards, 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, 1944, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - American Labor Committee, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Australia, 1951-1965 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Australia: Trip - Clippings, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Australia: Trip - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Bessarabian Jewry, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Bialystok, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Bialystok: Research by Nachman Blumental, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Chanin: Zionism & Communism, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - China (Mezhiborsky, D., memorabilia), 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Citizens Committee on Displaced Persons, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Citizens Committee on Displaced Persons, 1949-1957 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Reel 3
  - Common Council for American Unity, 1948-1957 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Conference: Goals of the Jewish Labor Movement, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Congress for Jewish Culture, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Diaries, 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Displaced Persons Act, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Displaced Persons Bill, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Displaced Persons Screening, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Erlich and Alter Case, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Exhibition: "Europe's Fighting Underground", 1940s (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - France: Mouvement National Contre le Racisme- pamphlets & newsletters, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - France: Protest of Soviet Anti-Semitism, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fund Transfer: European, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General Jewish Council, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Germany, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Held, Adolph - Speeches & Addresses, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hungarian Reports, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hungarian Rescue, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Immigration, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Immigration, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Immigration, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Reel 4
  - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), Jan 1945-Aug 1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - ILGWU, Sep 1945-Dec 1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Israel, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Italian-American Labor Council, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Jewish Labor Committee (JLC): General, 1942-1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - JLC: Ab. Cahan Fund, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - JLC: Correspondence, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - JLC: Correspondence, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - JLC: Correspondence, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - JLC: Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - JLC: Correspondence, 1951, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - JLC: Leivick Fund, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - JLC: Minutes of National Executive Committee Meeting (excerpt), 20 Nov 1943. "Report & Discussion on the General Jewish Conference" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - JLC: Printed Material, 1942-1974 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Reel 5
  - JLC: Reports, 1942-1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - JLC: Women's Division, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - JLC: Workmen's Circle Division, 1943-1951 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Labor Chest (AFL), 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - League for Human Rights, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Pat, Frieda, 1946-1978 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Patt, Emanuel, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Poland, 1937, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Report: "Some Confidential Information on the Last Days", undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Reports, Notes, & Writings, 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Retirement, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Soviet Jewry, 1940s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Vilna: Refugee List, ca.1940 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Warsaw Ghetto Exhibition (Pictorial Statistics), 1945 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Warsaw Ghetto Memorial, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Wise, Shmuel: "Jewish Workers' Movement in the United States", undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Workmen's Circle, Branch 303 ("Jacob Pat Branch"), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Workmen's Circle: Constitution, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - World Conference of Jewish Organizations, Mar 1963 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Yiddish Culture Organization, Jan 1945 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Yugentruf, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Series III: Photographs, circa 1930-1969
  - Album: Argentina and Brazil, Mar 1948 - Jul 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Album: Children's Home in Lodz (A gift from the JLC), 1946 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Canado, Trinidad and Brazil, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General (includes Szmul Zygielbojm), 1940s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Israel and Europe, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Israel and Europe (includes Golda Meir), 1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Oversize Portrait, undated (Box Tamiment Shared OS007, Folder 1)
  - Photographs from Correspondence, 1953-1956; undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Uruguay (Joint Distribution Committee), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Laskier, Kaplan, and Cukierman in German Military Uniforms, circa 1942, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 14)